Awesome.
I think we're live.
>> I think we are, too.
Welcome mental health family.
Wasn't sure if we were live again or if
we were alive before. So hopefully we're
alive. We're alive. Yes, we are alive.
But we are live. But welcome to Mental
Health Monday. Hey, we're so happy to
see all of you. Please put a one in the
chat if you're hearing us. Okay, we have
good audio. Just want to make sure
before we go uh any further. But hello,
Dr. White. Welcome.
>> Greetings. Greetings. Hope you're having
a great week so far.
>> Great. Your week has been good. That's
That's wonderful. Wait, your week.
Today's just Monday, so your Monday has
been good.
>> I guess it's felt like a week.
>> Wow, that's quite a Monday. that the one
day felt like a week.
>> Oh man. But it's all good. How about
you? How was your weekend?
>> My weekend was very chill. I had most
chill Sunday and to be honest wasn't
didn't I had clients today, but it
wasn't jam-packed. So, it felt, you
know, felt good. It was a good beginning
of a week.
>> Isn't boredom a luxury?
>> You know, I have to say when people ask
me, they say, "Oh, what's your
self-care?"
just to do nothing.
>> Absolutely.
>> That is such a luxury.
>> And I'm starting to I'm there's a hobby
that I am starting to mentally get into
that I'm going to start physically
getting into, and that's gardening. So,
I want to really get into it, but it's
like you got to learn so much. It's like
I you know, you don't Well, I guess
you'll you know, I can learn by um trial
and error, too, but I'm still trying to
learn enough. So that will I that's what
I'm really interested in. But right now
having a day to do nothing, it's amazing
self-care.
>> That's a gold mine. Oh my goodness.
>> Especially when it's a Sunday and I just
don't have to do anything. So anyway,
what's your what's your self-care?
>> Oh man. Uh my self-care some of the
things I really really enjoy I love
building a presentation. Um that is that
is fun. Like um building presentations.
So that's fun. Uh, I love a nice walk.
>> Okay.
>> Um, so we're we're close to the
university, so it's fun to walk around
the university.
>> Yes.
>> Um,
>> I suppose banter with Florence cuz she
is funny. Uh, so
>> you guys are funny together. Yes, you
guys are cute.
>> Well, thank you.
>> But yeah, she is she is funny and and so
it is fun to just talk and sometimes
enjoy time. So that's fun.
>> Well, that's great. Look at my good
friend Daniela from Sydney. Just saw her
a few weeks ago. Welcome, Daniela. It's
good to see you. What time is it there?
>> I And you know what, Daniela? I My me
and Ivor are just starting to catch up
on our sleep. I feel like our body is
finally getting back on like America
time, central time zone. But
>> like Australia messed us up. It messed
us up pretty good. So, but it's good to
see you. Please, everyone else, put
where you're viewing from. We love to
see where everyone's viewing from.
>> Danielle,
>> shout out to Clint. Shout out to Clint.
Clint's in the house.
>> I saw Clint when before we went live, I
saw Clint was on. It was like it it
doesn't feel like mental health Monday
if Clint isn't here.
>> I'm just saying. Right.
>> That's He's just been here with us for
three and a half years, which is great.
It's 11:10 a.m. Yeah.
>> Wow. The jet lag is intense. It was.
>> That's
>> So, yes, please, everyone else, let us
know where you're viewing from. We want
to say a special welcome to you. I was
mentioning to Dr. White um off air that
last week was it was fun to talk about
marriage, but we had some singles here.
We had a lot of questions about singles
and even had some singles meet up here.
>> Exactly.
>> This isn't the meetup ministry. We
actually have a ministry with Living Man
at Church. It's Meetup ministry. This is
actually mental health Monday. But hey,
if you meet up here, that's great.
>> So be it.
>> Then we're Yeah. So, we'll be taking
your questions about relationships,
marriage, sing, being single, all of it.
We'll be doing all of that. Okay. We
have Buford, Georgia. Welcome. They're
from Buford, Georgia. Good to see you
here on um mental health Monday. Um and
we know that you guys will start start
putting in the chat um as we are
starting Milton Freewater, Oregon.
I'm trying to think if I've been I don't
think I've been through there, but I
know I know I must I think I know
someone who lives near there because
I've heard of that before. And then
somebody Ivy put viewing from I have no
idea what that flag do you know that
flag.
>> Viewing like it's a Europe it's
somewhere in Europe I think.
>> You got me. Okay, Ivy, you are really
showing the limitations
of our like I mean but Atante I mean you
were just so well traveled so but no I
can't
>> but I don't know that flag it it's
giving it's giving Europe I feel like is
it
>> No I know it's not Spain Portugal maybe
Ivy
>> maybe her her name will clue us in Ivy
Alpuri so like what is that like Algeria
or
>> Yeah that's an interesting flag
>> yeah I don't know but we have Paula from
Lexington, Kentucky.
>> Great to see you here.
>> And yeah. All right.
>> That's awesome. Seattle,
>> I'm think.
>> Yes. Close to Seattle. Beautiful
Seattle.
>> Well, again, just going back to our our
topic on marriage. Oh, Thailand.
Oh, great. You know, welcome, Ivy.
You're our first to mental health
Monday. and has um vis has been a
viewing audience from Thailand. Welcome.
>> Okay, shout out Ivy. We are
>> and really Daniela being in Sydney and
Ivy being in Thailand. I mean I know
they're not terri it's not so far away.
I'm sure it's about 11 in the morning in
in Thailand as well. I have to say I
knew we were close in Thailand when we
were in Sydney because I had amazing
Thai food. Oh, really?
>> Absolutely amazing. I mean,
>> really,
>> even in the airport, can you believe
that? It was fresh like you were in a
restaurant. Like the curries were out of
this world. I I
>> Oh, that's amazing.
>> Good. Very good.
>> That's the strongest appeal for travel
to me is the food.
>> Is the food.
>> Yeah.
>> Especially when you live in the south
like me. Okay. No disrespect to this
house, but
>> but it is nice to go and and and eat
different food from different areas.
Okay, I better stop because I'm going to
get myself in trouble here. All right,
>> marriage. Maybe we I don't know if we
should recap. We're actually taking your
guys' questions and an we're taking your
questions on marriage, relationships,
and um even being single. And so, please
let us know what you're wanting to know.
Last week was really, really, really
good. You guys were answering really
good questions, asking really good
questions, and um it was it was just a
lot of fun to answer them. So, please
put that in the chat. I think we started
you started with me last week, Dr.
White. So, I think I'm going to start
with you and so be it. So be it. So be
it.
>> Ask you a marriage question. Goodness, I
should have thought of that before.
>> What do I want to ask you? What you've
learned in like 26 years of marriage?
Um.
>> Oh, yeah. It does
>> you.
Okay. Um,
what is the greatest lesson you've
learned in 26 years of marriage? I think
you're 26. I know you're right around.
You're
>> We're working on 26. Next July. We'll be
26.
>> Almost 26.
>> What is the biggest lesson you've
learned
>> that you wish you would have known when
you said I do? On the day you said I do,
you wish you would have known what or
somebody would have told you.
>> If I if I could make a t-shirt, it would
be whatever it takes.
>> So,
we talk a lot about roles. We think a
lot about roles. I'm gonna do X and
you're gonna do X and I'm gonna and the
concept I find the most helpful is when
you marry someone, think of it as
starting a firm.
Think of it as starting and and not just
a business, a firm,
>> you know, where everyone has an
opportunity to contribute. Mhm.
>> I wasn't I could have said role, but
it's really an opportunity to
contribute,
>> right?
>> And that opportunity at times will be
diverse
>> and will stretch you out of the common
way that you contribute.
>> And it's the most helpful when you
approach it from the standpoint of what
is the agenda of the firm? What will
move us down the road?
Well, then I need to do whatever it
takes.
>> Whatever it takes.
>> And I wish that would have been my
mentality
more so like right right from jump cuz I
think I was more focused on roles and I
would have been more frankly I would
have been more attentive I feel like and
and seeing how much she was contributing
because I think she kind of had that
mentality of whatever it takes. And so
if only one partner has that idea of
whatever it takes,
>> uh it can be very overwhelming as
opposed to when everyone in the family
is thinking
we are submitted to this goal.
>> Like we're submitted to this goal and
that that's what we're really submitted
to and it's whatever it takes. Oh my
goodness. and you're helping one another
and you're seeing each other as partners
and you're seeing everyone just move
towards that. That's what I that's my
greatest lesson in marriage.
>> Yes. Yes. And that's powerful. I don't
want to miss this. We have a viewer
watching all the way from Bosnia.
>> So that's welcome. So we're just very
international. We have Thailand and
Australia and Bosnia. We're just all
over the place. It's wonderful. All over
the world. Welcome. And I see somebody
talking about Peruvian food. Now for you
Americans, we still got strong love for
the Americans. We love the Illinois. We
love the the Long View, Texas. So much
love. Much love.
>> Um, so and we love the International
Scope as well. But yeah, we we we we we
love you all. We love the greatest
Washington.
>> You know what's funny, Dr. White? You
know, I can I'm not very filtered. When
you were doing that, I thought you were
going to be like, "We love we love the
Americans," which we do, and we love
their food. And I was going to be like,
"We do."
>> No, but but but southern
>> What is American food? Honestly,
>> like southern cooking, your mac and
cheese. Oh, let's make it vegan. Fine.
>> I mean, because I don't really do all of
that. I mean, if I can make a vegan
version, of course.
>> Your sweet potatoes. I mean, they got
their
fresh fried. I mean like I mean we're
not championing like eating meat and all
this kind of stuff. We know. But I mean
no, they got their thing now.
>> We're gonna bring Dr. Batist back on.
>> Did you Did you know that it's rumored
that it's the G? Like Cuz I don't know
if you've ever tasted like really really
good um Yeah. Fried, you know, chicken.
What is it from Korea? I think it's like
from Korea. Apparently the GIS when they
went over to Korea like they gave them
the recipes of their like mothers, you
know. Oh, so they can make
>> That's why it's so legendary and it's so
so good. That's a rumor, though. Don't
Don't ask me the evidence-based. Don't
ask me for the article.
>> It's a rumor that you're just spreading
internationally right now. But
>> but anyway, but I guess we're just
talking along the lines of food and how
interesting foods show up. Anyway,
sidebar.
>> Okay. Clint's like, "Let me get them off
of food and back to
>> Exactly. Exactly." All right, Clint,
welcome. All right. So, what are some
balancing principles we can use for our
marriages while raising four kids? What
are some balancing?
>> I think you're asking He's asking us,
but I think I should answer,
>> especially as someone who's had the
better part of four years.
>> We had four We have, praise God, four
kids. Um,
so what this is this is this is I have
to say this is God because from the very
beginning
of our marriage and this is before and
we still had things we needed to learn
and work out because we just didn't
really know everything obviously. But we
because we were in ministry, we had
heard about a uh
a couple that was in ministry and and
always traveled and was very well known.
Um but they traveled so much the
ministry encompassed both of them. So
the husband would go this way and the
other the wife would go that way because
they were trying to cover as much
ground. They were basically the ministry
was like overtaking their life basically
and they ended up in divorce and it was
really sad. So
It's that was a very unfortunate event
and a sad event for them, but it spoke
to both of us and we were like, we're
never going to um allow the ministry to
take over because we have the four kids
and we have ministry. So, we made we
made it a point and praise God again
that we had family, my parents,
grandparents, you know, just family that
could always watch the kids so that we
could go away uh maybe once a quarter or
just several times throughout the year
to have our time together and not just
have to always be like raising kids and
doing ministry. So, I would say one of
the principles that we learned is to is,
you know, to have time to make sure you
have time for yourself. And as as the
kids got older, we were able to just go
on weekly date nights, but that was
later on that we learned to do things
like that. You know what I mean? That
was late that was much later on. Um, but
just to always be pouring into our
marriage by making sure we spend time
just with for us because four kids is a
lot.
>> Yeah.
>> And a ministry. That's a fifth kid.
>> We had five kids.
>> And that that's the one that's the
>> church. That's six kids.
>> That That's a selfish kid. Like they
just it it requires a lot. You ever see
the pictures where it's like mom's on
this side, then you have the four kids,
and then dad's on the other side.
>> And like you've got to in my opinion, my
humble opinion, you've got to fight
that. You can't let anything come
between you and your spouse. It's like
it's that's what everything is built on.
And you see it going in both directions
where where at times the marriage can
kind of melt away as this tornado called
kids will just threaten to just take it
over
>> and bless them. I love them. But
>> yeah, you can't let that you can't let
that happen. Um, the other thing I would
say is there's something about working
with a person in the trenches. There's
something about that. And I would say
whether it's whoever the spouse is, it's
like get in the trenches with your
spouse. Like wherever possible, don't
let someone else do that. Get in the
trenches with them because it is it
it bonds you. It really well like
there's there's a reason that these
executives often end up with their
secretaries. There's a reason there's
something about a person continuously
coming through for you
>> and idolizing you and you know get in
the trenches.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and uh and it's something that bonds
you and it blocks other people from
getting in the trenches. It's like no no
I got that
>> I got that out the person. Uh that that
to me is
don't let things melt the marriage.
Don't let like tornadoes come in and
blow apart the marriage. Like let crisis
push you push you to gather even closer.
>> And you know, I was just thinking about
how you said some of your self-care is
taking a walk, but I was just thinking
even because the things I brought up,
people are like, "Oh, well maybe we
can't we can't go on weekly date nights.
we don't have anybody to watch our kids
or we can't go away like once a quarter
because we don't have anybody to watch
our kids. You know, even if you spend
daily time with each other like going on
a walk together, you know, simple things
like that, holding hands, that's very
important. Like taking a walk, holding
hands, um just making sure that you're
spending that quality time and you
create what that looks like according to
what's going on in your life. It doesn't
have to look what like what we did or
what other people do, but what would
make it's what you can do because
sometimes all four kids are very very
young. It makes it difficult, but maybe
your time is going to be after you put
them to bed,
>> right?
100%. I remember for our date nights, we
didn't have to leave the house,
especially with our daughter.
>> Like, we didn't have to leave the house.
like it was it was getting her on a
system to where she was going to be down
relatively early so you would then have
that time for yourselves,
>> right?
>> But you you got to use that noggin, use
that creativity, everything you have to
fight for that pres fight for that
relationship. And it's, you know, fight
preserve that. I call it virgin love.
You remember when you guys first started
dating? You remember when you first
started dating where you didn't even
want to be seen in a certain way? Like
like fight to preserve that, man. Fight
fight because it's a it's a beautiful
thing to preserve as much as it's
possible.
>> Yes, it is.
>> All right. And we all know, well,
Deborah's asking, we all know uh that in
a marriage both people may have to
compromise, but can you name a few
situations where it can become unhealthy
and you have to stop?
>> Well, that's pretty simple.
>> That's pretty simple.
>> Um, violence, that's when you can't
compromise with.
>> Absolutely not. And and what's
interesting is people would know well
violence but then also and Deborah this
really kind of comes down to what are
some boundaries that are like
non-negotiables.
If you're like, "We don't want physical
violence,"
then you actually have to draw the
boundary at things like yelling
>> or throwing things like
>> if the boundary is here and you don't
want it crossed, you've got to really
make it like way way further back. So,
the person never even gets to here. And
that's where if you're like, I don't
want physical violence in my
relationship, then we don't want verbal
violence because
um that that protects it from getting to
that point. We we want people in control
of themselves.
>> Um but no, there there there are
definitely areas that I I don't see very
much room for negotiation. Uh safety
safety is a big one for me. I think it's
important for me that the women in my
family and around me feel safe.
>> Um, so safety is important. Uh,
>> that's part of the reason I personally I
don't I don't drink alcohol. I don't I
don't want my ability to control myself,
>> excuse me,
>> impeded in any way, you know, um, or
other substances for that matter.
>> Um, but I know I'm responsible for
myself and for their safety. So,
>> right,
>> those would be some non-negotiables for
me. Uh, Deborah,
I think respect. I don't see a lot of
places to negotiate when it comes to
respect.
>> Like, you really have to know this is
what I value is respect. And
>> so, I I don't absolutely
>> I hope that's helpful.
>> Yeah, those are those are areas um that
just Yeah, that just pop up right off
the first thoughts for sure. Um, my
non-Christian parent uh met on a blind
date, got engaged three days later and
eloped. They've been lovingly married 53
years. Wow.
They say marriage and life was so
different back then. Is that really
true?
We were babies back when your parents
got married. I I wasn't even born when
your parents got married. I don't know
if it was really
>> true. I was like negative three.
Yeah. Um I'll keep it right. I am older
than you. Always forget that. Um so
things were different back then. Um
what what your parents did is you know
that that it worked for them. Worked for
them and they're still married and
hallelujah. Praise God that you had two
loving parents stay together.
>> Not recommended.
>> Yeah. But yeah, we could wouldn't
recommend but it worked for them but
everybody can't do that. I mean I have
to do disclaimer I say the same thing
like
>> we were me and my husband were engaged
after two months
>> and I tell my kids and I tell when we
ever when we're speaking or give that
testimony I tell them like this was for
us. This is not for you unless God
you can hear his voice audibly and say
oh yeah I want you to marry this person.
And we weren't married within two months
but we were engaged. We were married
within like 11 months, which is almost a
year, but still that's pretty quick. Um,
and you did say you heard,
>> like I said, it was for us, but it's not
for everybody. Go ahead.
>> You did hear God's voice, right?
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And I I
should add that on. Sorry. Let me add
that. Uh, yes, most definitely. I
remember I'll never forget I always tell
I always tell my husband cuz he didn't
know I was doing this but I just
remember like I just blocked out a whole
day and I went to a park and I took my
Bible and I prayed and I talked to God
to like show me different things and um
he gave me peace. So
>> profound.
>> There's more to that story but
>> profound. Now Amber, now that now Amra,
did your parents
involve God? Was it like did God give
them permission or did they just get
left?
>> She just said they're they my
non-Christian parents. They're still not
Christians, but they're lovely people.
>> They they might still pray to God even
though they're not Christians, though.
>> Only Emry knows that. I don't know.
>> Yeah, they may pray to God. But but but
the bottom line is whether you marry 10
years from now or you marry one year, it
it's really wise to involve God in the
process.
>> Oh yes.
>> You know,
>> absolutely. And I guess that is you're
right. Um of course you're right, Dr.
White. I mean that is the
that's the ingredient that has to be in
there because um
>> you're even Yeah. If you're gonna if you
just met them and you hear God's voice
saying like, "Yeah, this is it." Okay,
then that that's okay. You're hearing
God's voice. If if you're right, if it's
three, four years down the road and you
hear God's voice, this is this is the
person, then it's okay.
>> Amber is hilarious. She said, "No, my
mom prays on Thanksgiving."
>> I kind of knew she was going to say
something because I I've met her
parents. I Well, I've met I can't say I
know them, know them, but I've met them
and I've heard all of a lot of Ammer's
stories, so I figured the answer was
going to be no.
[Music]
All right, let me see.
>> Oh, a single person. We love our
singles. I'm single. However, what is
the best way to handle conflicts or
disagree disagreements? Is it just
communication or just compromise or both
or something else entirely? Great
question. Great question.
>> I'm going to take a quick stab at it. Um
>> so it's definitely uh communication
the comp compromise like what we just
mentioned earlier would have to be
extremely
minimal like to what we talked about
meaning I and I let me tell you why I
say that if you have healthy
communication
you can say anything to your partner in
a healthy
way if you're you know if If you are uh
you know we use what um Gottman uses a
soft startup. So you're you're not
triggering try you know you're talking
to them in a soft tone. The body
language is speaking softly to them.
Everything is just a non-aggressive type
of communication. And um Dr. Dr. Gman
talks about with a soft startup, you get
what you want out of that communication
because you're not triggering their um
their walls to go up or their defense.
They're not like, "Oh, it's I'm in a
fight, so I got to, you know, not a
physical fight, but a verbal fight. I
got to put my walls up." Um they don't
feel that way. So, um, sometimes you
have to compromise, but the m, but
really, if you're approaching your while
you're dating and your partner in a
healthy with healthy communication, you
probably won't even need to compromise
because their heart is open to hearing
what you have to say. Go ahead. Um, I
agree with I agree with what you said
and rather than the word compromise, I
would use the word consensus because you
can't say, well, you know, I want the
house blue
and you want the house whatever color
and we'll make the house purple as
compromise, you know. Um, no. You got
to, so you got to build consensus.
Meaning, we need a sensible decision
that might not necessarily
um be this perfect blend of both of our
ideas because the perfect blend might be
crazy. And so, no, we actually need
consensus. We need to arrive at a
conclusion that makes the most sense.
Um, so I think you're spot on as far as
uh communication. Mhm.
>> I think I'm not going to take you
through a communication workshop right
now, but I will say
>> um communication 101 is a heavy use of
what are you hearing me say?
>> Way too underused is that thing. What
are you hearing me say? And here's what
I'm hearing you say. And that's
basically called tracking. Uh, a lot of
times we're so focused on conveying our
ideas that we are not really listening
to the person and we're not passionate
about giving the person the experience
of being heard.
>> I'm telling you right now, it's one of
the greatest gifts you can give to your
partner, to the to the to the other
member of the Dad, the other member of
the pair is
>> I feel so heard. It's hard for a person
to resent you when you make it clear, I
really and truly hear you.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and that that's something super
important. And obviously and also when
you do that, it makes it clear what you
need to give into
>> like okay, I hear you. You're not
budging from this and now I understand
why you're not budging. Okay, well this
is how I can accommodate that. So, uh, I
would say those are things that are
really important and I hope in this
little time that we're spending on this
topic, RSA, good heavens, RSA 1844.
Okay. Okay. You go. Um,
I hope in this little time you're seeing
the value that could go into investing
and learning in this area, sometimes
spending some time with a therapist
because I'll tell you why. RSA. Um,
sometimes part of stuff from the past
makes it hard to hear.
>> Sometimes stuff from the past will
interfere with your hearing and you'll
hear things the person didn't say.
You'll feel things the person didn't
say. What What are you thinking? What
are you thinking, sis? Well, I was just
thinking because while you're talk like
well because the stuff that the stuff
could be coming up for them like while
you're talking they're thinking of like
oh no but back then she said or she did
this or he did this. So they're coming
up with a rebuttal or you know they're
thinking all of those instead of just
that's not true listening. That's not
really listening. Um you have to I was
just sharing this yesterday with a group
of people but you have to drop your
weapons. You know what I'm saying? You
have to come into a relationship.
>> I I I don't think you've ever been
arrested. I've never been arrested, but
they say put your hands up or, you know,
drop your weapons or whatever. You have
to come into the conversation
like empty-handed. You're not
>> That was really good. Drop your weapons.
Drop your weapons. That was really good.
Um Yeah. Like you can't hear the person
without that. Like so it's like it's
really like listen to give the person
the experience of being heard, not give
the not not listen to respond and you
know the difference. You know the
difference because like the person's
mouth is already open and you barely
stopped speaking. You you're not to hear
you know
>> and they're like jump in real quick.
Man, that's what I wish I would have
learned at the very beginning of the
marriage. I wish I would have learned to
drop my weapon.
>> Oh wow. Okay. you know, because you're
just thinking, you know, you don't
really know how to communicate
in the healthiest way when you first
start.
>> Yeah. That's what Gotman says. That's
what Gotman says. He's like, it's not
fighting, it's how you fight.
>> Yes.
>> Um, and it's not ruptures, it's how you
repair the rupture.
>> Yes. Absolutely. Absolutely. We have
another question. What can you do if
you're married and your spouse keeps
going past the boundaries such as name
calling while arguing?
>> Yeah, that's absolutely a boundary that
should not
>> ever be crossed.
[Music]
>> We keep bringing up Gotman when we're
talking about marriage. But um you know,
he also talks about um talks about this
specifically as well. I mean, if that
continues,
um,
>> you're already at a level where the
respect is not there. The disrespect is
is there. There's just not a high amount
of respect. Um, and
those are steps to at some point, I
mean, unless some some intervention
comes in that the marriage is going to
continue to get further and further or
the two individuals will get further and
further apart. And so
when you're in that type of situation,
it's definitely the time to call someone
to get some outside help. And I would,
you know, any licensed marriage and
family therapist, any, you know, just
therapist that can work that works with
marriages, it's definitely time to to
get some help.
>> So Paula, I don't know how often you've
come to mental health Mondays, um, but
we have frequently
>> Is it Paula? Yeah, Paula.
>> It's Paula. But but but we've frequently
made references to Gottman, so we may as
well just give you the backdrop. Um Dr.
John and Julie Gottman are the famous
founders of the Gottman Institute, and
part of their claim to fame is that they
say that after analyzing even five
minutes of a couple's interaction,
um they can with 93% accuracy determine
if they will still be married in five
years.
And one of the things that they identifi
or some of the things that they
identified that would contribute to
divorce were what they call the four uh
horsemen of the apocalypse. Mhm.
>> And one of them was contempt,
another was criticism, another was
stonewalling,
and the fourth one is
um I don't know that I'm going to think
about it right this instant, but the
bottom line is it sounds like what
you're describing is like criticism. and
they they they identified criticism as
it's one thing to
describe a behavior and it's another
thing to kind of attack a person's
character. Um and of course insults can
often not just attack the behavior but
they kind of attack the person. And so
they said when these four horsemen show
up there's an increased risk of the
relationship um failing. So this is why
Sister Tante is saying, "Hey, um these
can be signs that it would be a great
idea to get some professional support um
to figure out how best to negotiate what
sounds like a really trying situation.
>> Yes. Would definitely would not hurt.
Yeah. And I'm sorry, Paula, that is
happening." And
>> I'm super sorry.
>> Yes. It's not It's never no fun to to be
in that um situation. For sure. For
sure. Just want you guys to know that we
are taking your uh your questions um
even comments at during this time. You
help uh the program, you help it go, you
help it work. So, we love answering your
questions. Go ahead.
>> So, I'm doing a presentation on heaven.
Okay.
>> Yes. Tell us about that. And um if
you're interested, just email me at
info@themastermind institute.
info@themastermind institute. And so it
bothers me
>> that's happening when?
>> Friday the third Friday the 31st. So
this Friday. This Friday.
>> Okay.
>> This Friday.
>> All right.
>> So thank you so much. Um but yeah, I've
I've never attended a sermon
specifically on heaven. You know, it's
like it's very rare. And some of the
questions like you know um what are
meaningful things that will happen in
heaven? Uh what will communication be
like? What will what will intimacy look
like in heaven?
>> Um you know these are some of the
questions that we are going to deal
with. Um and why is it even
>> if we can't go live? Is it going to be
recorded?
>> Yeah. Email me. Email me and we we'll
figure it out. Info at the math
institute. But um but so we're going to
do 400 pm Eastern Standard Time, but we
are going to do an encore presentation
at 700 p.m. Pacific Standard Time. So
>> 7 so just think 700 p.m. Eastern and 700
p.m. Pacific um standard time and and if
you're interested, if this is something
that you're interested, just email me at
info@themastermind
institute. But just a topic that's near
and dear to my heart. Yeah.
>> Sounds great. Sounds amazing. Okay, we
have questions. What if a couple dating
feels led by God to get married, but one
of the partners still has reservations
because of their different communication
styles? How to tell if it's fear or
something more? H, good question. And
I'm glad you're asking, and I'm glad you
guys are thinking. marriage is a huge
huge step and commitment um that should
not be taken lightly. So kudos to you
guys for really taking it very serious.
Do you want to take a stab at it first?
I
>> after you after you I mean unless you
want me to but yeah go ahead.
I mean again we only God can can tell
you
only God can tell you if this person is
for you and you guys are to be married
right so you spending time in prayer
hearing God's voice is very very
important um but I as a um marriage and
family therapist I have to say I you
know I do premarital counseling or even
people who are dating and I always you
know talk out. Don't ignore red flags.
Don't ignore red flags. Now, maybe the
red flags need you don't ignore them.
Maybe they're just something that you
can deal with. And when I say deal with,
I mean like have a conversation about
it. If you're in uh well, I I recommend
premarital counseling before you get
engaged. like pre before you engage
counseling
because once you're engaged and you've
like put money down on the venue and
bought a one, it's just much diff it's
very difficult to step away if you have
to. So my point is um if there's a red
flag and and you learn about it while
you're dating, you really want to if
you're Christians, of course, you want
to pray about it. You can also go to
therapy to to see if this thing can be
worked out. And if you're finding like,
you know what, this is just who this
person is and they're not willing to to
change or they don't see anything wrong
with it or whatever. I mean, that could
be your answer to step away. I'm not
saying that it is. I'm just saying that
you don't want to just sweep something
under the rug before you get married
because it's going to come out from
under the rug while you're married and
it could cause some se some severe
unhappiness for you. What are your
thoughts, Dr. White? Well, I know you're
going to join me in this because and I
think all good married couples will
raise their hands right now and let you
know um nothing to see over here. And
what I mean what I mean by that is
um there are so many couples that that
are afraid of breaking up. like they're
afraid that oh my goodness if I break up
you know I literally have to treat
people who after a breakup they're like
suiciding and stuff like that and like
guys guys guys let me tell you
>> um
there what a favor you do for yourself
>> when you end a relationship and like
there's really no reason for it not to
be amicable. It's like this this is
opening the door for you to be able to
find the person that's right for you.
>> That's a gift.
>> That that's a gift. Because so many
married people, so many people on this
side are miserable.
>> Yeah.
>> Are miserable. Yes.
>> And yes, there are some rare situations
where it starts miserable, but most of
the times it starts with like some
really powerful infatuation,
>> right?
Like more often than not, it's you can't
keep your hands off one another and you
can't you got just all this love bombing
and all this kind of stuff.
>> And it goes from that to sexless
marriages,
>> right?
>> Like it's the most shocking and
counterintuitive thing like people
sleeping in opposite rooms of the house
and all this kind of stuff. And I'm I
promise you they're looking at and
they're saying, "If only."
>> Yeah.
>> If only. And so so there is this myth
that single people have that like it's
this horrible thing if we break up. No,
it is a wonderful
>> gift you're giving to each other. It's a
wonderful gift you're giving to each
other where you have another
opportunity. I I have good news for you.
I have good news. There are four billion
people of the opposite sex on the
planet. Good news, there's hope. I
promise you, there
>> there is hope. There is four billion
people. Okay?
>> And I like to tell people too,
especially young people when I worked at
the university because, you know, young
adult, they're they definitely don't
want to break up. But I'm like, look, if
it's if this is God's will for you, if
this relationship is for you, even if
you break up and it's God's will, it'll
come back around. It'll come back around
when you're both healthier in a right
better space. I mean, I'm not saying
that happens all the time, but you can
still put it in God's hands and trust
him with it, but you don't want to rush
into anything and stay in a relationship
that you're already seeing some
unhealthy habits. And if it's the
communication, because this person said
like it it could be the communication
piece that's, you know, causing so much
that is causing all the issues. The
communication piece just has veins that
travels throughout the whole
relationship. It connects everything. If
you're not if you don't have healthy
communication, you're not going to have
a happy relationship, a happy marriage.
>> It's kind of the tip of the iceberg.
Yeah. And I love to tell people like you
dodged a bullet like like they because
some you know if if some if if you you
break up because you saw something and
you're finding like several months later
you're actually happy and at peace, you
dodged a bullet and you have to say
praise God to that.
>> Amen.
>> We have questions. We have How do you
find contentment with being single?
Good. Good first part of the question. I
will be 42 soon and I've been single
seven years. My clock is ticking and I
don't have a potential suitor. How can I
continue to be patient?
>> This is like loaded loaded with a lot of
>> so loaded. I love it. I love it that you
guys are Thank you. You guys are That's
a very good question though.
>> So, first of all, contentment with being
single. Look, um,
first first and foremost, I think if
you're single, then you think about,
okay, well, what is the partner that I'm
desiring? Okay.
>> Well, then the next question has to be,
well, what
does that partner that I desire desire?
What do they want? Okay. Mhm.
>> And then let me position myself to give
them that thing in abundance. Okay. Let
me So I don't know. I've been married
for about 25 years. I am still very very
very motivated to be a competitive
suitor to my spouse. I'm very very
motivated
>> to be the obvious choice, you know. So,
it's like I really am excited at the
prospect of of providing,
>> of being present, of giving her what it
is that she wants. That that excites me.
>> Um, and that it's that same mentality.
If I were if I were single, you're
you're wanting to position yourself. You
want to say, "Wait, who is it that I'm
after? What would they want? I want to
embody that thing as much as possible."
And this is what I mean by when I
started my relationship. When I started
my relationship, I was more focused on
what I wanted
>> and as I've grown older, as I've
matured, I am now really interested in
what that person wants and positioning
myself to give that.
>> So that that's the first part. So, and
and I guess the contentment piece is
man, put the energy into being that
person into like put that energy like
and do I have that? Do I have the spirit
that they would find valuable?
>> All of the things that they would f oh
my goodness. And you got to be
realistic. You got to be realistic. You
might even want to just talk to a person
with those ass like the person that
you're like, you know, I would be really
interested in that person. pull them
aside and talk to them. Just talk to
them. Be like, "Hey man,
>> what is it that you want? What is it
that you would desire?" Real talk, no
judgment. What would you really value?
>> What are the non-negotiables for you?
You know,
>> and I think that a lot of people are
scared of doing that. So, they presume
they know what the person wants without
documenting this is what they want and
then positioning themselves to give it.
I'll be 42. You wanted to jump in, sis?
>> Well, that this is the same question. I
just want to say really quick, and we've
talked about it on here, that this is
the time, like you're saying, this is
the time that while you're single, is to
pour into all the self-help books, um,
about how to become a good spouse, um, a
good husband or wife, um, and even going
to therapy, even just to deal with your
own individual things that, um, you're
realizing
could be an issue. like this is the time
to do that work so that when that person
comes into your life, excuse me, I have
a tickle in my throat, you will be ready
to be that person that they are needing
and for the relationship to be amazing.
So these single years are not to be
wasted.
>> There's a work to be done. There's a
work to be done. Look at it like you're
preparing for
>> you're preparing yourself for the
marriage
>> passionately and do that passionately.
Yes.
>> And you're praying and you're praying
that God and the Holy Spirit puts it on
the person that's for you on their
heart. So they're doing that the same
thing. So when that you come together
>> put that back up, Amber, we just did
with we just dealt with the first part
of the question.
>> Oh, you're right. That was a that was a
loaded question.
>> We just we just warming up. Come on,
Amra.
>> All right, there we go. Then she said,
"I will be 42 soon and I've been single
seven years, but the the part I really
want to deal with is my clock is ticking
and I don't have any potential suitors.
Let's deal with that."
>> So, a lot of times
the suitor that's interested in you,
you're not interested in them.
>> So, it's not necessarily true you don't
have suitors. Sometimes what you're
shooting for
>> um might not be all that available and
sometimes person might have been
adequate but like the people that you're
shooting for. So now let's say for
example I'm shooting for like a 10 like
a 10 in terms of like like dude so a lot
of the things that come with a so-called
10 um you might not be able to deal
with. Now I'm married to a 10. I'm just
I'm just messing around just in case
you're watching Florence. Right. Right.
But like but like yeah if you the some
of the issues that you have to deal with
at that you know
>> rating
um kind of makes relationship
impractical
and so sometimes you kind of have to
modify and realize wait a second when I
think about the life that I want to live
that's more congruent with this
particular rating and when you when you
get down to this particular rating you
might see there's actually a person that
you might be ignoring and you didn't
really see as viable, but they're
actually viable. They're a decent
person,
>> right?
>> And now this isn't to say Kiran Mech
that this applies to you, but there are
people who have broken picker syndrome,
>> right?
>> And some of the and and and and the good
guys are boring. Like they like the guys
with a little edge or the girls with a
little edge, you know? And it's like
like there it's broken picker. Like a
lot of times like people have been like
wounded from the past. So yet again you
got these wonderful people surrounding
you but you're not interested in
>> you're not even interested. Not even
>> you're not you know I don't have any
viable suitors. You got like three
people in the friend zone. You got this
other people in your DMs but you're not
interested. And so
>> it's it's kind of reaclimating. And
again that might not apply to you but I
think there's some listeners for whom
this might apply. And so that's why
sometimes you got to fix the broken
picker, get the therapy, heal the trauma
so that you can reaclimate to
>> No, it's not boring when a person says
they're going to show up at 6 and they
show up at 600. No, that's a good thing.
It's it's not boring that a person's
dependable. And I'm not going to give
kudos to the person who they just show
up whenever they want. And I'm so glad
that they showed up because they finally
show. No, you got to recondition
yourself.
>> So,
>> absolutely. No, that was great. That was
a great answer to her three-part
question,
>> right?
>> Um I know. Yes. Can we please because
we're our time is slipping. It's You
guys have great questions. If we don't
get to all of them, come back next week
because it's like we're doing a series
on on relationships here. What are your
thoughts about both partners coming to
the conversation where you both agree
that you're not enemies, you both want
the best for each other and focus on
feelings rather than actions.
>> We kind of talked about that before
where it's like don't don't demonize the
breakup. Don't realize don't view this
as toxic or awful. And there's one other
thing like if you really really love the
person
>> and they're saying to you, I don't want
to be with you, right? Rather than
making it about you, like if you really
love them, don't you want them to be
happy or would you rather? Nope. Nope.
Nope. I need you to just love me even
though you've made it clear I'm not
quite your cup of tea.
>> Right. Well, you're missing the
opportunity to get to your audience that
celebrates you. There's an audience that
celebrates you. Sometimes you just got
to be patient to find it or you have
some evolving to do also,
>> right?
>> But the bottom line is love them enough
to leave them and let them leave. Love
them enough to leave them and let them
leave on a good note. And I got a secret
for you. I got a secret for you.
>> Sometimes it's when you remove yourself,
again, sometimes, not always. Sometimes
it's when you remove yourself from the
situation and the person gets to
experience the full weight of your
absence
>> that they get a chance to decide, hey,
do is do do I really want a life without
this person or do I want them in it?
>> And with you constantly chasing, they
never really got a chance to see what it
would be like for for them to be without
you,
>> right?
>> Um, so just some things to consider.
>> Yes. Excellent answer. Excellent answer.
All right, we have time for
one maybe two more questions. How can I
help two of my friends who are in the
world and are in a relationship but
almost six months and are thinking about
marriage to realize they are probably
making a mistake. It is a worldly
marriage. Um,
you said you said they're both they both
don't have a relationship with God. So,
um,
it's really
they Okay, I I'm I'm I'm I'm words are
about to come out my mouth and I and I'm
I'm rechecking them a little bit.
Meaning, because I don't want to be
misunderstood,
but it's not really
our place to to say that. And I'm not
saying that you're wrong. You're
probably right.
Um, and these are two friends that, like
you said, they're both I guess they're
both your friends and they're in the
world. I mean, they're basically equally
yolked. Do you understand what I'm
saying? Do you understand what I'm
saying, doctor?
>> I understand exactly what you're saying.
Like, I was I was waiting to see how you
were going to do it because because the
question kind of ropes the question
makes some assumptions that if you're in
the world, you can't have a successful
marriage,
>> right? That's not true.
>> These like the principles of
communication, there's a science to
communication,
>> right? And you could be an atheist, you
honor these principles and you'll be
fine,
>> right?
>> Um,
>> absolutely.
>> So, so, so that's where just because
you're in the world, it doesn't mean
you're going to have a bad relationship.
The bottom line is there are some
fundamental things. Do you respect one
another? Um, do you love one another?
Um, do you make sure you hear one
another? Do you prioritize each other?
Right?
>> Um, or are you selfish? Because I'll
tell you right now, there are a bunch
there are a lot of Christians
>> um who are very uncchristian in how they
interact with one another and the
relationship.
>> Uh so so it's not it's not just the
world, it's
are you honoring the principles that
support a relationship and a
>> respect? Do they respect each other? Do
they treat each other with respect? Do
they show respect? That's huge. they
prioritize each other? Do they? And
that's agnostic. Doesn't matter what
religion you're in. Doesn't matter
whether you believe in religion or not.
The bottom line is
>> it it's like it's like it's like
business success,
>> right?
>> Like there are some laws to having a
great business. And it is it doesn't
it's agnostic. It doesn't matter what
religion you are. You honor these laws,
you'll have a great business. Doesn't
matter how religious you are. If you
dishonor these laws, you won't have a
good business because God set up laws.
This whole earth is governed by laws.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, yes, hopefully that
helps as a friend,
>> right? So, yeah, if you're
>> pray for them and just continue to be
there for them,
>> encourage therapy, you know,
>> encourage them, right? Okay. I if I ever
get married now, okay, this is Robert.
Uh what will we do?
What will we do if our parenting styles
or values conflict? Any best way to
handle this? First of all, yes. If you
ever think that you want to ask somebody
to get married or you're thinking about
that, I want you to go to premarital
engagement counseling because you can
talk about those type of things. Those
are the type of things you discuss. You
don't want to find out the parenting
style when you're in the once you're in
the marriage. You want to have those
discussions,
you know, before you get married or
before you even get engaged and say,
"Hey, this is what I think um this is
how I believe I'm going to raise my
children or this is how I'm going to
discipline or whatever." Um, and you
want to have that discussion because
that's huge. That's huge.
>> I hope they caught the pre-engagement
counseling.
>> It's super unfair to approach a
therapist, hey, um, we've got the
wedding scheduled. We've picked the
venues. All of the family have bought
their tickets and we would like some
counseling, you know, before we get
married.
>> I know it's kind of frustrating to be
>> and like that's the that's a frustrating
place to put a person in. She said
pre-engagement.
So before all that because counseling
might show you that you guys don't
belong together,
>> right?
>> And it's an unfair position to put a
counselor in after you've kind of
stacked the deck. No. Pre-engagement. So
the point being, Robert, you have these
conversations beforehand because if
there's no meeting of the minds, you
fill in the blank, Robert.
>> Yes, that was a great question though.
>> Great question.
>> And that will be our last question of
the evening. You guys are I'm enjoying
this. It um you guys you guys are
bringing the you guys are asking very
good questions. Um please come back with
your with these questions. Don't forget
uh your questions and we will definitely
would like to answer them answer them
next week. But share this link, share it
on your social media. Say, "Hey guys,
this is a great program on marriage."
Tell them you can see what was done
these last last week, the last two
weeks, and they can bring their
questions live next week. So definitely
share with um everyone even if they're
single or married. This is good
information to know. So, we just want to
thank you all of you for joining us this
evening and we look forward to seeing
you next week. Byebye, sis. Have a great
week.